Grace Shattuck Bail Papers
Grace Shattuck Bail Papers
1942-1979
Bail, Grace Shattuck.
2.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American poet, composer, arranger. Bail often set Biblical passages to music. Collection includes correspondence (1942-1979); musical compositions, poems, and memorabilia.
148824
Biographical History
Grace Shattuck Bail (1898-1996) was an American pianist, violinist, musicologist, and poet. A member of the American Poetry League, N.L.A.P.W., Eugene Field Society, Mark Twain Society, Chaparral Poets, and many other professional organizations, Bail's published works included compositions, songs, poems, and books. Her work appeared in periodicals such as Evening Star (Washington, D.C.), Etude, Arizona Highways, Listen, The American Bard, and The Pen Women, as well as occasionally in such non-mainstream publications as the horror/fantasy monthly Weirdbook.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Grace Shattuck Bail Papers are comprised of two separate accessions which have not been integrated.
The original accession contains two series: Correspondence, 1944-1965, and a few Subject files (awards, copies of poems, published pieces, clippings).
The 1980 accession consists of four series. Correspondence contains correspondence from 1942-1979. Memorabilia includes biographical information, a photograph, and other items. Published material contains reviews and clippings. Writings is the largest series and contains books, music, songs, and poetry.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Subject files are arranged alphabetically by topic. Memorabilia and writings are arranged alphabetically by type; writings are further arranged alphabetically by title. Note that since the two accessions have not been integrated, box numbers are not unique; please specify box number and accession when requesting material.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Poetry; Music; Bail, Grace Shattuck Archives.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Church music.; Sacred vocal music.; Women composers, United States.; Women poets, American.; Correspondence.; Musical scores.; Poems.; Composers.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Grace Shattuck Bail, 1967-1984.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1944-1945, 1947 (Box 1)
  - 1953-1955 (Box 1)
  - 1957-1965, 3 folders (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Awards (Box 2)
  - Biographical material (Box 2)
  - California Federation of Chaparral Poets, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
- Correspondence (1980 additions)
  - 1942-1979 (Box 1)
  - undated (Box 1)
- Memorabilia (1980 additions)
  - Biographical information (Box 1)
  - Lists (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Photograph, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Poetry judge name card (Box 1)
- Published material (1980 additions)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Reviews (Box 1)
- Writings (1980 additions)
  - Books
    - Cantabile, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Golden Days, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Heartstrings, 1968; 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - Music
    - "A-Mour" (Box 2)
    - Anthem, "Morning Song" (Box 2)
    - "April Day" (Box 2)
    - "Autumn" (Box 2)
    - "Ballet" (Box 2)
    - "Beatitudes", 1954 (Box 2)
    - "The Betrayal - John Chapter 18 - Chapter 19", 1955 (Box 2)
    - Cantatas
      - "Galatians Chapter 1", 1954 (Box 2)
      - "John, Chapter 3", 1954 (Box 2)
      - "John, Chapter 10", 1954 (Box 2)
      - "Peter's denial foretold - John, Chapter 13", 1954 (Box 2)
      - "Psalm 3", 1955 (Box 2)
      - "Psalm 8", 1955 (Box 2)
      - "Psalm 9", 1955 (Box 2)
      - "I Thessalonians, Chapter 5 - II Thessalonians", 1954 (Box 2)
      - "The way, the truth and the life - John, Chapter 14", 1954 (Box 2)
    - "Christ further comforts his disciples - John, Chapter 16", 1955 (Box 2)
    - "Christmas morning", 1955 (Box 2)
    - "Christ's prayer to be glorified - John, Chapter 17", 1955 (Box 2)
    - "Clarissa" (Box 2)
    - "Consolation" (Box 2)
    - "I Corinthians, Chapter 6 - Chapter 8", 1954 (Box 2)
    - "Cradle music for baby", 1963 (Box 2)
    - "The Crucifixion - Mark, Chapter 15" (Box 2)
    - Cycle from cantata - "Psalm 91" (Box 2)
    - "Desert Wind" (Box 2)
    - Flute - "Song of the flute" (Box 2)
    - "Genealogy of Noah - Genesis, Chapter 5 - Chapter 7", 1954 (Box 2)
    - "Genesis, Chapter 10 - Chapter 11", 1955 (Box 2)
    - Harp - "Etudes for harp" (Box 2)
    - "Harvest" (Box 2)
    - "Hebrews, Chapter 1 - Chapter 4", 1954 (Box 2)
    - "Hushaby" (Box 2)
    - "Isaiah, Chapter 55", 1954 (Box 2)
    - "Job, Chapter 13 - Chapter 14", 1954 (Box 2)
    - "John, Chapter 8", 1954 (Box 2)
    - "Little Tunes" (Box 2)
    - "Love on another - John, Chapter 15" (Box 2)
    - "Minuet for two violins" (Box 2)
    - "Miss you so" (Box 2)
    - "Naïve" (Box 2)
    - "Noah's Ark - Genesis, Chapter 7 - Chapter 9", 1954 (Box 2)
    - "Nocturne", 1955 (Box 2)
    - "Only a dream" (Box 2)
    - Oratorios
      - "Creation - Genesis, Chapter 1 - Chapter 3", 1954 (Box 2)
      - "Galatians, Chapter 2 - Chapter 3", 1955 (Box 2)
      - "Palm branches - John, Chapter 12", 1954 (Box 2)
    - Organ or piano - "Summer Day", 1955 (Box 2)
    - Piano
      - "Chaconne" (Box 2)
      - "The dream" (Box 2)
      - "Dutch iris" (Box 2)
      - "Interlude", 2 folders (Box 2)
      - "Low tide", 1945; revised 1955 (Box 2)
      - "Overture enfatico" (Box 2)
      - "Regret" (Box 2)
      - "Soliloquy", 1956 (Box 2)
      - "Soliloquy I" (Box 2)
      - "Theme" (Box 2)
      - "Whispering leaves", 1955 (Box 2)
      - "White lilacs", 1957 (Box 2)
    - Piano duet - "Ballet", 1956 (Box 2)
    - "Psalm 7", 1955 (Box 2)
    - "Psalm 27", 1955 (Box 2)
    - "Psalm 91", 1954 (Box 2)
    - "Psalm 105" (Box 2)
    - Quartet for women's voices - "Endwing spring", 1956; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - "Rain drops" (Box 2)
    - "Reflections" (Box 2)
    - Sacred chorus - "Praise to our Father" (Box 3)
    - "Sea lore" (Box 3)
    - "Sleepy song" (Box 3)
    - "The spring" (Box 3)
    - "Story for baby", 1959 (Box 3)
    - String quartets
      - "Cherry blossoms", 1956 (Box 3)
      - "Melody", 1956 (Box 3)
      - "Nocturne", 1956 (Box 3)
      - "Penseroso", 1956 (Box 3)
      - "Spring morning", 1956 (Box 3)
      - "White iris" (Box 3)
      - "White roses", 1956 (Box 3)
      - "Wild wheat", 1956 (Box 3)
    - String trios
      - "Allegretto", 1956 (Box 3)
      - "Cantabile", 1956 (Box 3)
      - "Nocturne", 1956 (Box 3)
      - "Romance", 1956 (Box 3)
      - "Serenade", 1956 (Box 3)
      - "South wind", 1956 (Box 3)
    - Bb trumpet with piano - "Woodland song" (Box 3)
    - Tuba
      - "Larghetto" (Box 3)
      - "Romance", 1956 (Box 3)
    - "Valse dream" (Box 3)
    - Violin and piano
      - "Caprice", 1959 (Box 3)
      - "The mocker's song" (Box 3)
    - Violin solos
      - "California poppy" (Box 3)
      - "Cavatina", 1955 (Box 3)
      - "The crystal stream", 1968 (Box 3)
      - "Golden poppy" (Box 3)
      - "Larghetto", 1956 (Box 3)
      - "Love song" (Box 3)
      - "The mocker's song", 1965 (Box 3)
      - "Spring morning", 1976 (Box 3)
      - "Theme", 1969 (Box 3)
      - "Twilight" (Box 3)
    - Vocal
      - "How can one sleep?", 1965 (Box 3)
      - "Spring song" (Box 3)
    - Vocal (medium voice) - "The babe" (Box 3)
  - Poetry
    - Miscellaneous, 1966-1972 (Box 4)
  - Published songs
    - "A bird sings in May", 1971 (Box 4)
  - Published poems
    - "A president's dream", 1969 (Box 4)
    - "April hour", 1971 (Box 4)
    - "August night", 1968 (Box 4)
    - "Forever and ever", 1969 (Box 4)
    - "Gentle hand", 1969 (Box 4)
    - "In memory of Grace" and "To a friend", 1967 (Box 4)
    - "Joyous water ouzel", 1969 (Box 4)
    - "Love", 1967 (Box 5)
    - "Mass for a deer", 1977-1978 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1965-1978 (Box 5)
    - "My heart remembers", 1971 (Box 5)
    - "Nocturne", 1978 (Box 5)
    - "One day", 1969 (Box 5)
    - "Safe harbor", 1978 (Box 5)
    - "Singing poems anthology", 1968 (Box 5)
    - "Solo", 1978 (Box 5)
    - "Spring brought me gifts", 1972 (Box 5)
    - "Tunneling scalopus", 1970 (Box 5)